MAURICE GOODMAN

PhD Candidate · Marine Ecology





SUMMARY -

As a PhD candidate studying marine ecology and biogeography at Stanford's Hopkins Marine Station, my work uses a variety of statistical and computational approaches to examine climate impacts on population and predator-prey dynamics in coastal marine systems to inform conservation and fisheries management. Prior to beginning my PhD, I worked as a data analyst and field technician for community ecology and behavioral ecology labs at Cal Poly, San Luis Obispo.

ossingy table at out toty, our Euro obiopor			
EDUCATION ————————————————————————————————————			
2018 - Present	PhD Candidate in Biology Advisor: Giulio De Leo Stanford University		
2013-2017	B.S. Biological Sciences, Cum Laude California Polytechnic State University SLO Concentration in Marine Biology, Minor in Statistics		
PUBLICATION:	s ————————————————————————————————————		
In Review	Gissi, E., Goodman, M.C. ,, Micheli, F. <i>Sex-based species interactions matter in ecological communities.</i> Trends in Ecology and Evolution		
In Review	Goodman, M.C. et al. Title withheld pending double-blind peer review. Biological Conservation		
In Review	Rempel, H.S. et al. <i>Ecological drivers of parrotfish coral predation vary across spatial scales.</i> Marine Ecology Progress Series		
2023	Faiad, S.M., Williams, M.A., Goodman, M. ,, Wood, C.L. <i>Temperature affects predation of schistosome-competent snails by a novel invader, the marbled crayfish Procambarus virginalis</i> . PLoS One, 18(9). doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290615		
2022	Goodman, M.C. et al. <i>Shifting fish distributions impact predation intensity in a sub-Arctic ecosystem.</i> Ecography, doi.org/10.1111/ecog.06084		
2022	McCalla, L.B. et al. <i>Effectiveness of a Constructed Wetland with Carbon Filtration in Reducing Pesticides Associated with Agricultural Runoff.</i> Archives of Environmental Contamination and Toxicology, doi.org/10.1007/s00244-021-00909-0		
2021	O'Leary, J.K., Goodman, M.C. , Walter, R.K., Willits, K., Pondella, D.J., & Stephens, J. <i>Effects of Estuary-Wide Seagrss Loss on Fish Populations.</i> Estuaries and Coasts, doi.org/10.1007/s12237-021-00917-2		
2020	O'Leary, J.K., Goodman, M. , Tuda, A., Machumu, M., & West, L. <i>Opportunities and challenges in achieving co-management in marine protected areas in East Africa: a comparative case study.</i> Journal of the Indian Ocean Region, 16(3). doi.org/10.1080/19480881.2020.1825201		
2019	 Hart, L., Goodman, M.C., Walter, R.K., Rogers-Bennett, L., Shum, P., Garrett, A.D., Watanabe, J.M., & O'Leary, J.K. Abalone recruitment in low-density and aggregated populations facing climatic stress. Journal of Shellfish Research, 39(2), 359-373. doi.org/10.2983/035.039.0218 		
2019	Goodman, M.C. , Hannah, S.M., & Ruttenberg, B.I. <i>The relationship between geographic range extent, sea surface temperature, and adult traits in coastal temperate fishes.</i> Journal of Biogeography, 46(7), 1438-1450. doi.org/10.1111/jbi.13595		

OTHER RESEARCH WORKS

Book Chapter O'Leary, J.K., Bockman, E.E., **Goodman, M.**, Grimsditch, G., Madej, M.A., Mohammed, A., & Tyburczy, J. **Goodman, M.C.**, Adams, N. (2024). *Conserving and Managing Estuaries during Climate Change. In Book: Climate Change in Estuaries*. In Press.

Manuscript

Lippert, M., **Goodman, M.C.**, Adams, N. (2021). *Comparative effects of Chemical and Physical Sunscreen on Fertilization of Purple Sea Urchins (Strongylocentrotus purpuratus).* Cal Poly Digital Commons, digitalcommons.calpoly.edu/biosp/44

Technical Report O'Leary, J.K., Tuda, A., Machumu, M., Nyunja, J., & **Goodman, M.C.** Technical report to the Western Indian Ocean Marine Science Association. Developing a model for strategic adaptive management of MPAs in the Western Indian Ocean. 34 pp.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE -

2022-Present Independent Contractor

NOAA AFSC / University of Washington

Built species distribution models for a suite of Eastern Bering Sea groundfish and crab species as part of the Alaska Integrated Climate Modeling (ACLIM) project. Produced species range and spatial overlap projections under multiple earth systems models. Created an R "Shiny" based web app for navigating outputs (mgoodman.shinyapps.io/aclim2_sdms_explorer). Currently preparing results for submission to a peer-reviewed journal.

2022 **Independent Contractor**

Granite Canyon Marine Labs

Analyzed data from experiments aimed at reducing wetland agricultural runoff. Produced figures and contributed to writing of peer-reviewed manuscript summarizing results.

2017-2018 Data Analyst & Field Technician

California Sea Grant

Responsible for the analysis, management, and visualization of ecological and social data from Tanzania, Kenya, and Morro Bay, California in the lab of Dr. Jennifer O'Leary. Assisted with writing reports and manuscripts. Full-time.

2016-2018 Summer

Research & Dive Technician

Cal Poly SLO

Worked alongside Dr. Ben Ruttenberg to conduct benthic surveys and fish follows on SCUBA to characterize coral community and document parrotfish feeding behavior in St. Croix, USVI. Responsible for entering and managing photo, video, and GPS data, and for gear and boat maintenance. Seasonal.

2016, 2018 Aquarist

Central Coast Aquarium

Assisted in managing, training and mentoring volunteers and interns in the husbandry department. Maintained all tanks and systems, collected and acclimated new animals, curated exhibits, and regularly monitored water quality. Part-Time.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2022, 2023 Instruct

BIO / OCEANS 143: Quantitative Ecology

Developed and taught 3 weeks of labs and lectures based on material I designed for the previous years' course (see below), focusing on frequentist parameter estimation and species distribution modeling. Assisted students with labs and assignments and graded student submissions.

2021 **Co-Instructor**

BIOS 207: Software Engineering for Science

Cod-developed materials for teaching software development concepts (code documentation, version control, modular programming, testing and validation) for "Just Enough Software Engineering for Science" short course. Led discussions, assisted students with programming challenges, and evaluated student assignments.

2021 **Teaching Assistant**

BIOHOPK 143H: Quantivative Ecology

Designed and taught 3 weeks of labs and lectures on parameter estimation for nonlinear and dynamic models using frequentist and Bayesian principles, as well as species distribution modeling with GAMs (github.com/mcgoodman/quant-eco-2021). Assisted students in learning material taught by other course instructors, held weekly office hours, and assisted students in designing and executing final projects. Awarded Stanford School of Humanities and Science's "Centennial" Teaching Award and Stanford Biology's "Excellence in Teaching" Award.

2019 **Teaching Assistant**

BIO 85: Evolution

Co-developed lesson plans, teaching materials, homework assignments and tests. Led a section where students reveiwed and reinforced material from lecture, held weekly office hours, and graded student assignments. Awarded Stanford Biology departments "Excellence in Teaching" Award.

Prepared lab specimens and activities for class, collected new specimens, demonstrated lab methods and dissections to students, and assisted students with lab and field activities.

OUTREACH, LEADERSHIP, & SERVICE

2022 - 2023 President Hopkins Marine Station Graduate Student Association

Engaged the graduate student community in multiple community-building initiatives, including organizing inclusivity trainings, social events, and graduate student retreats, representing grad students to Dean and Hopkins faculty and administrative and DEI meetings, and obtaining funds to renovate grad student work & social spaces. Previously served as webmaster for graduate student association (Fall 2019 - Summer 2021).

2020-2022 Student Liaison MARINE

Served for two academic years as Hopkins Marine Station's liaison for Monterey Area Research Institutions' Network for Education (MARINE), an organization of of marine science students and early career researchers from seven academic institutions in the Monterey Bay area. Planned networking, social, and community service events.

2016-2017 Founder & Vice President Cal Poly Marine Science Club

Founded and co-lead the Cal Poly Marine Science Club. Organized, planned, and lead events and meetings; managed social media and outreach.

2014-2018 Husbandry & Outreach Volunteer Central Coast Aquarium (Non-Profit)

Assisted with husbandry tasks such as maintenance of tanks, acclimation of fishes, treatment of diseased fishes, curation of exhibits, preparation of diets, and training of new volunteers. Frequently gave talks and tours to the public, taught grade school programs, and participated in outreach and fund raising. **Over 800 hours volunteered.**

FELLOWSHIPS, HONORS, & AWARDS

2022-2024	Graduate Scholar 50% Tuition & Salary sup	port Stanford Data Science
2022	Research Grant \$6,500	Friends of Hopkins Marine Station
2022	Research Grant \$1,800	Myers Oceanographic & Marine Biology Trust
2021	Excellence in Teaching Award	Stanford Department of Biology
2021	Centennial Teaching Award	Stanford School of Humanities & Sciences
2019-2023	Graduate Research Fellowship Tuition & S.	alary Support National Science Foundation
2014-2016	President's List	Cal Poly College of Science & Mathematics
2016	Summer Research Scholarship \$2,500	William & Linda Frost Foundation, Cal Poly SLO
2016	Undergraduate Research Grant \$500	CSU COAST

PRESENTATIONS

2023

Talk Goodman, M.C. et al. Shifting fish distributions impact predator-prey interactions in the Eastern Bering sea. Alaska Marine Science Symposium.

Talk Goodman, M.C. Global shark fin demand, small-scale fisheries, and reef sharks: A case study in the Northern Line Islands. Stanford Data Science Conference.

Talk Goodman, M.C. et al. Shifting fish distributions impact predation intensity in a sub-Arctic ecosystem. Ocean Sciences Meeting.

- Talk Goodman, M.C., White. T., Kazdan, J., & De Leo, G. International market demand drives a small-scale Central Pacific reef shark fishery towards collapse. Western Society of Naturalists.
- Talk Goodman, M.C. et al. Ecological consequences of climate induced changes in spatial overlap between Eastern Bering Sea walleye pollock and their predators. Western Society of Naturalists.
- Talk Goodman, M.C., Hannah, S.M., Ruttenberg, B.I. (2017). The Relationship Between Geographic Range Extent and Adult Traits in Coastal Temperate Fishes. Western Society of Naturalists
- Talk Goodman, M.C., Hannah, S.M., Ruttenberg, B.I. (2017). The Relationship Between Geographic Range Extent and Adult Traits in Coastal Temperate Fishes. Cal Poly Annual Student Research Symposium.
- 2017 **Poster Goodman, M.C.** et al. (2017).*Long-Term Monitoring of Sea Urchin Settlement Along the California Coast.* Cal Poly Annual Student Research Symposium.
- Talk Goodman, M.C., Hannah, S.M., Ruttenberg, B.I. (2017). The Relationship Between Geographic Range Extent and Adult Traits in Coastal Temperate Fishes. Central Coast Wildlife Society Annual Wildlife Symposium.
- 2017 **Poster Goodman, M.C.**, Hannah, S.M., Ruttenberg, B.I. (2016). The Relationship Between Geographic Range Extent and Adult Traits in Coastal Temperate Fishes. Western Society of Naturalists

FIELD RESEARCH

2023 NOAA Alaska Fisheries Science Center Bering Sea Bottom Trawl Survey

Volunteered on a three week survey leg sorting, sexing, and lengthing specimens as part of the annual Eastern Bering Sea bottom trawl survey which collects data needed for stock assessments and other management models. Lead stomach collection for food habits analysis.

2019-2023 **Stanford Hopkins Marine Station**

Various Projects

Palumbi lab: Assisted on field projects in Palau (collecting corals and running heat stress experiments, transplating corals for common garden experiments) and the California central coast (collecting samples via boat on SCUBA, processing samples). **Other:** Various dives to conduct kelp forest ecological surveys and deploy instrumentation for graduate student projects.

2014-2018 Cal Poly San Luis Obispo

Ruttenberg & O'Leary Labs

Ruttenberg lab: Collection of coral reef ecological survey data via SCUBA (see Work Experience section), and surveys of Pismo Clam populations on California coastal beaches from Port San Luis to San Diego. **O'Leary lab:** Monthly collection of cobbles via SCUBA for monitoring recruitment of abalone, surveys of eelgrass and associated fish communities via beach seines and monitoring of permanent plots.

SCUBA Experience & Certifications

AAUS Scientific Diver, 60 ft

PADI Divemaster Now Inactive

DAN Diving First Aid for Professional Divers

2015 - Present
2017 - Present
2015 - Present
2015 - Present

MENTORSHIP

2019, 2022 **REEFS Undergraduate Internship**

Stanford University

2022: Mentored two undergraduate students in building out a control system for conducting multiple stressor experiments in aquaria, developing protocols as part of a pilot study, and analyzing data. Students prepared and presented poster to researchers and other students at Hopkins. **2019:** Mentored an undergraduate student in applying machine learning and statistical approaches to model harmful algal bloom incidence in California.

Established and led a biweekly sea urchin recruitment monitoring program at Port San Luis as part of the larger Santa Barbara Coastal LTER project. Trained several undergraduates in deploying collection media and sorting and identifying specimens.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Scientific Computing

R, R Markdown, & RStudio, Stan, GIS (QGIS, R sf & stars packages), git & github

Statistical Methodology

Bayesian and frequentist linear, nonlinear, and dynamical models; hierarchical, time-series, and spatial models; R statistics packages (rstan, brms, mgcv, glmmTMB, nlme, lme4, VAST, etc.)

Software Development

R Shiny web apps

ACLIM2 SDMs explorer: mgoodman.shinyapps.io/aclim2_sdms_explorer Probability distributions lab: mgoodman.shinyapps.io/distributions-lab

Reproducible Scientific Code Repositories

Faiad et al. 2023: github.com/wood-lab/Faiad_et_al_2023_PLoS_One Goodman et al. 2022: github.com/mcgoodman/Goodman-et-al_2022_Ecography Andrzejaczek et al. 2022: github.com/mcgoodman/shark-vertical-overlap O'Leary et al. 2020: github.com/mcgoodman/OLeary-et-al_2020_ESCO

R Packages

geomViolinDiscrete: github.com/mcgoodman/geomViolinDiscrete

SCHOLARLY REVIEWS

2024	NOAA Internal Review
2023	Fisheries Research, Marine Ecology Progress Series, PLoS One
2022	Progress in Oceanography, Animal Biotelemetry, NOAA Internal Review
2021	ICES Journal of Marine Science
2020	Nature Scientific Reports